Guide to the Dennis Cooper Papers ca. 1970-2002 MSS 085
© 2012 Fales Library and Special Collections
Dennis Cooper Papers
1970-2002
MSS 085
© 2012 Fales Library and Special Collections
20.0 linear feet (25 boxes)
The Dennis Cooper Papers cover his career from approximately 1970 to 2002 and include correspondence and manuscripts of many notable literary and cultural figures, scrapbooks, manuscripts, collaborative projects, journals, journalism, reviews, business/production files for each book project, posters, videocassettes, and tapes. Dennis Cooper's creative output includes poetry, journalism and fiction that at times explores 'extreme subjects.' In the late 1970's, Cooper became involved with the nascent punk scene and began Little Caesar Magazine, and later, Little Caesar Press. He is the author of novels such as: Closer (1989) and Frisk (1992), has contributed to the Village Voice, Spin, The Advocate and L.A. Weekly, and co-curated an exhibit with Richard Hawkins entitled "Against Nature: A Group Show of Work by Homosexual Men." Presently, Cooper lives in Los Angeles.
Provenance
The Dennis Cooper Papers were purchased in June, 1997 from Cooper. Arrangements for the sale of the collection were negotiated through Ira Silverberg, literary agent for Cooper. Cooper initially organized the collection and packed the materials for shipment. The Library received a grant that allowed for the purchase of the collection.
Access Restrictions
Open to researchers. Written permission must be secured for researchers to consult the J.T. Leroy photographs. Appointments are necessary for the use of manuscript and archival materials.
Historical/Biographical Note
Dennis Cooper was born on January 10, 1953 in Pasadena, California. His literary aspirations were explored early on and often took the form of imitations of Rimbaud, Verlaine, De Sade, and Baudelaire. He wrote poetry and stories in his early teens that explored scandalous and often extreme subjects. As a teenager, Cooper was an "outsider" and the leader of a group of poets, punks, stoners and writers. After high school he attended Pasadena City College and later Pitzer College where he encountered a poetry teacher who was to inspire him to pursue his writing outside of institutions of higher learning.
In 1976 Cooper went to England to become involved in the nascent punk scene transforming the visual/verbal aesthetic of punk into its written counterpart--see, for example, Closer. In the same year he began Little Caesar Magazine which included among other things an issue on and dedicated to Rimbaud. In 1978 with the success of the magazine, Cooper was able to found Little Caesar Press which featured the work of, among others, Brad Gooch, Amy Gerstler, Elaine Equi, Tim Dlugos, and Eileen Myles.
In 1979, Cooper became the director of programming at an alternative poetry space, Beyond Baroque, in Venice, California. During his tenure such artists as Tim Miller, Eric Bogosian and Jessica Hagedorn gave performances. He also curated shows that included works by Sheree Levin and Bob Flanagan, Peter Schjeldahl, Kenward Elmslie, Gerard Malanga, and Jack Skelley. In 1984, Cooper moved to New York City. In 1987 he met his Dutch boyfriend whom he soon followed back to Amsterdam. While exiled in Amsterdam he finished writing Closer which took as inspiration a postcard that featured an image of Mickey Mouse carved onto the back of a young boy. Cooper later won the Ferro-Grumley for gay literature for Closer.
While in Amsterdam he also wrote articles for different American magazines including the Village Voice. He soon returned to New York and began writing articles for Artforum and began working on his next novel, Frisk. In the next few years Cooper works on several different art and performance projects including co-curating an exhibit at LACE with Richard Hawkins entitled AGAINST NATURE: A Group Show of Work by Homosexual Men.
Presently, Cooper lives in Los Angeles. He has, after his final return to Los Angeles from New York, collaborated with a number of artists, including composer John Zorn, painter Lari Pittman, sculptors Jason Meadows and Nayland Blake, and others. In the Spring of 2000 he published the final novel, Period, of the series that began with Closer, followed by Frisk, Try, and Guide.
BIBLIOGRAPHY:
The Terror of Earrings. Arcadia, CA: Kinks Press, 1973.
Little Caesar. Ed. Dennis Cooper. Los Angeles: Little Caesar Press, 1976-1981.
Tiger Beat. Los Angeles: Little Caesar Press, 1978.
Antoine Monnier. Los Angeles: Anon Press, 1978.
Idols. New York: The Sea Horse Press, 1979.
Coming Attractions: An Anthology of American Poets in Their Twenties. Ed. Dennis Cooper with assistance by Tim Dlugos. Los Angeles: Little Caesar Press, 1980.
The Missing Men. Santa Barbara: Am Here Books/Immediate Editions, 1981.
The Tenderness of Wolves.Trumansburg, New York: Crossing Press, 1982.
My Mark. Los Angeles: Sherwood Press, 1982.
Safe. New York: Sea Horse Press, 1984.
Them. (play) Produced in New York, 1985.
He Cried. San Francisco: Black Star Series, 1985.
Against Nature: A Group Show of Work by Homosexual Men. Curators Dennis Cooper and Richard Hawkins. Los Angeles: Los Angeles Contemporary Exhibitions, 1988.
Closer. New York: Grove Press, 1989.
Idols. Revised Edition. New York: Amethyst Press, 1989.
Knife/Tape/Rope (play). produced in New York City, 1989.
The Undead (play). produced in Los Angeles at Mark Taper Forum, 1989.
Frisk. New York: Grove Weidenfeld, 1991.
Lust.Intro. Dennis Cooper. Los Angeles: The Advocate Liberations Publications, 1991.
Discontents: New Queer Writers. Ed. Dennis Cooper. New York: Amethyst Press, 1992.
Wrong: Stories. New York: Grove Weidenfeld, 1992.
Jerk. San Francisco: Artspace Books, 1993.
Try. New York: Grove, 1994.
Dear Dennis, Love Lari. Collaboration with Lari Pittman and Jonathan Hammer. San Francisco: Hammer Editions, 1995.
The Dream Police: Selected Poems, 1969-1993. New York: Grove Press, 1995. Horror Hospital Unplugged. New York: Juno Books, 1997.
Guide. New York: Grove Press, 1997.
Weird Little Boy. Collaboration with John Zorn, Nayland Blake and Casey McKinney. Tokyo and New York: Avant Records, 1998.
Raymond Pettibon. Intro. Dennis Cooper. Switzerland: Kunsthalle Bern/D.A.P., 1998.
Period. New York: Grove Press, 2000.
Raymond Pettibon. Intro. Dennis Cooper. New York: Phaidon, 2001.
Thom Friedman. Essay. Dennis Cooper. London: Phaidon, 2001.
My Loose Thread. Edinburgh: Canongate Books, 2002.
Scope and Content Note
The Dennis Cooper Papers is comprised of the correspondence and manuscripts of many notable literary and cultural figures, scrapbooks, manuscripts, collaborative projects, journals, journalism, reviews, business/production files for each book project, zines, posters, videocassettes, tapes, and materials from both Little Caesar Magazine and Little Caesar Press. The Cooper Papers contains an almost comprehensive collection of the early to present-day literary career of Dennis Cooper. Cooper's original organization of his papers was preserved as much as possible.
Original format for most materials.
SERIES DESCRIPTIONS
SERIES I: Book projects and related materials
subseries A contains 4 boxes of book project materials, including promotional materials, business records, manuscripts, reviews, scrapbooks, correspondence, and background materials.
subseries B contains 1 box of collaborative projects and works edited by Cooper. This subseries includes manuscripts, correspondence, business materials, photos, promotional materials, reviews, a CD and slides.
subseries C contains materials relating to Cooper's collaborative projects including a play written with Haasen and collaborations with Houston-Jones.
SERIES II: Book Projects and Correspondence of Writers and Artists
Contains the manuscripts, correspondence, reviews, promotional materials, interviews, slides, readings and announcements, clippings and newsletters of friends and colleagues of Cooper.
SERIES III: Journalism
Contains journalism written for magazines and newspapers including but by no means limited to Artforum, The Advocate, Art in America, Spin, and The Village Voice. Series 3 also contains journal articles that either remain unpublished or contain no information regarding the publications for which they were written.
SERIES IV: Biographical material
subseries A contains biographical materials including juvenilia, diaries, scrapbooks, a headshot, college materials, readings, reviews and correspondence from family members.
subseries B contains personal correspondence, including early rejection letters.
SERIES V: Beyond Baroque
Contains materials from Cooper's tenure at Beyond Baroque including correspondence, readings, reviews, writing workshop materials, press materials and photos.
SERIES VI: Little Caesar Magazine/ Little Caesar Press
subseries A contains materials relating to and of Little Caesar Magazine including correspondence, invoice and records, reviews, press materials, production materials, and mock-ups of several issues of the magazine.
subseries B contains all the materials relating to and of Little Caesar Press including manuscripts, mock-ups, cover art, posters, photos, and correspondence.
SERIES VII: Media Material [Access copies may not be available for these materials yet. Check with the Fales archivist.]
subseries A contains all access copies for videotapes available to researchers.
subseries B contains all original video recordings given by Cooper including versions of "Knife/Tape/Rope" and Frisk. [Also see ACCRETION 2002]
subseries C contains all access copies for audio material available to researchers.
subseries D containts all original audio material given by Cooper.
SERIES VIII: Zines
Includes zines collected by Cooper.
SERIES IX: Posters
Contains posters of readings, announcements, and promotional advertisements. The Posters are located in the map case.
OVERSIZE:
There are 2 flat oversize boxes that contain oversize materials from series 6.
ACCRETION 2002:
The 2002 Accretion to The Dennis Cooper Papers focus on Period, the last installment of Cooper's George Miles cycle and My Loose Thread, his first full-length prose work outside said cycle in ten years. The accretion includes scrapbooks, manuscripts, notebooks, and videotapes relating to these works. In the case of Period there's a model house constructed of wood and filled with a hand-drawn representation of the novel's structure, a note to Ziggy, and images of haunted houses, George Miles, and various anonymous teenagers. Also included is a diaristic scrapbook on "Ideal Beauty."
The collection also makes available Cooper's Death and Sex File, which includes clippings from hundreds of magazines and newspapers spanning more than a decade.
There are a number of folders of Juvenalia from the 1960's and 1970's, including early poetry, journalism, prose, journals, correspondence, and Cooper's first novel written when he was an adolescent.
The correspondence in the 2002 Accretion includes photos of the reclusive author J.T. LeRoy and materials regarding Cooper's newest editorial project, the Little House on the Bowery series at Akashic Books.
Arrangement
For the most part, folders are arranged alphabetically by subject/author within each series.
Items of similar subject/format are grouped together in the 9 series with some exceptions. Oversized material is arranged together.
Series I: Book Projects and Related Materials
Series II: Book Projects and Correspondence of Writers and Artists
Series III: Journalism
Series IV: Biographical Material and Personal Correspondence
Series V: Beyond Baroque
Series VI: Little Caesar Magazine/Little Caesar Press
Sereis VII: Media Material
Series VIII: Zines
Series IX: Posters
Oversize Materials Series I: Book Projects and Related Materials
Oversize Materials Series II: Book Projects and Correspondence of Writers and Artists
Oversize Materials Seris IV: Biographical Material and Personal Correspondence
Oversize Matierals Series VI: Little Caesar Magazine/Little Caesar Press
Oversize Series VIII: Zines
Map Case
ACCRETION 2002 - Series I: Book Projects and Related Materials
ACCRETION 2002 - Series II: Book Projects and Correspondence of Writers and Artists
ACCRETION 2002 - Series III: Journalism [Includes Tearsheets of Articles]
ACCRETION 2002 - Series IV: Biographical Material and Personal Correspondence
ACCRETION 2002 - Series VII: Media Material
ACCRETION 2002 - Series IX: Posters
Oversize Material ACCRETION 2002 - Series I: Books and Related Materials
Oversize Materials ACCRETION 2002 - Series IV: Biographical Material and Personal Correspondence
Related Material at the Fales Library and Special Collections
Tim Dlugos Papers
Serpent's Tail/High Risk Archive
Between C& D Archive
David Wojnarowicz Papers
Separated Material
Printed books in the collection have been removed and catalogued individually as part of the Downtown Collection.
Bellamy, Dodie; Boone, Bruce; Brite, Poppy Z.; Clark, Tom, 1941-; Cooper, Dennis, 1953-; Dlugos, Tim; Equi, Elaine; Fecteau, Vincent; Gerstler, Amy; Glück, Robert; Gooch, Brad, 1952-; Hawkins, Richard, 1961-; Home, Stewart, 1962-; Indiana, Gary; Jeppeson, Travis; Killian, Kevin; LeRoy, J.T., 1980-; Pera, Brian; Sedaris, David; Silverberg, Ira; Skelley, Jack, 1956-; Stadler, Matthew; Stark, Frances;; Tillman, Lynne; Trinidad, David, 1953-; Waters, John, 1946-; Weissman, Benjamin; Wojnarowicz, David; American literature |y 20th century.; Artists and community |z United States.; Authors, American |y 20th century.; Avant-garde (Aesthetics); Beyond Baroque Literary Arts Center.; Business records.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Diaries.; Gays' writings, American.; Literature, Experimental.; Little Caesar Press.; Little magazines.; Los Angeles (Calif.); Magazines (periodicals); Manuscripts for publication.; New York (N.Y.); New York (N.Y.) |x Intellectual life |y 20th century.; Poets, American |y 20th Century.; Posters.; Reviews (document genre); Scrapbooks.; Scripts (documents); Small presses |z California |z Los Angeles.; Sound recordings.; Venice (Los Angeles, Calif.) |x Intellectual life |y 20th century.; Video recordings.
- Series I: Book projects and related materials
  - Subseries A: Book projects and related materials
    - Terror of Earrings, manuscript, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Terror of Earrings, reviews, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Tiger Beat, correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Tiger Beat promotional material, undated (Box 16, Folder 4a)
    - Tiger Beat, reviews, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Antoine Monnier, manuscript, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Idols, manuscript, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Idols, manuscript--typewritten with revisions, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Idols, correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Idols, contract, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Idols, JFK Jr. scrapbook, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Idols, JFK Jr. scrapbook cont., undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Idols, press and reviews, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Tenderness of Wolves, first draft, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Tenderness of Wolves, early draft, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Tenderness of Wolves, manuscript, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Tenderness of Wolves, correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 15a)
    - Tenderness of Wolves, contract, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Tenderness of Wolves, reviews, undated (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - The Missing Men, correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - He Cried, manuscript/review, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - He Cried, correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 20a)
    - My Mark, early draft, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - My Mark, correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 21a)
    - My Mark, background--Mark Lewis File, undated (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - My Mark, reviews/promotional material, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Safe, early drafts, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Safe, cont., undated (Box 1, Folder 24a)
    - Safe, final draft, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Safe, manuscript, undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Safe, correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Safe, contract, undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Safe, reviews, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Safe, production, undated (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Closer, early drafts, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Closer, later draft, undated (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Closer, galleys, undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Closer, correspondence, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Closer, contract, undated (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Closer, reviews, undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Closer, press/production, undated (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Closer, material on Closer, undated (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Frisk, early manuscript "Tense", undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Frisk, early drafts, undated (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Frisk, early drafts, undated (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Frisk, early drafts, undated (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Frisk, draft, undated (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Frisk, draft, undated (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Frisk, manuscript, undated (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Frisk, correspondence, undated (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Frisk, imagery, undated (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Frisk, background material--Keanu Reeves file, undated (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Frisk, background material--draft of Keanu Reeves interview by Cooper, undated (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Frisk, background material--manuscript of Keanu Reeves interview by Cooper, undated (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Frisk, reviews/promotional material, undated (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Frisk, reviews/promotional material, undated (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Frisk, reviews/promotional material, undated (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Frisk, Passagen promotional material, undated (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Frisk, unpublished essay by William Burroughs on Frisk/Closer, undated (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - Frisk, essay by Achy Obejas on Frisk, undated (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - Frisk, related manuscript--author unknown, undated (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Frisk, film script draft, undated (Box 3, Folder 61)
    - Frisk, film script final version--first draft, undated (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - Frisk, film script final version--second draft, undated (Box 3, Folder 63)
    - Frisk, film script--Todd Verow version, undated (Box 3, Folder 64)
    - Frisk, film publicity/promotional material, undated (Box 3, Folder 65)
    - Frisk, death threat pamphlet, undated (Box 3, Folder 66)
    - Frisk, film reviews, undated (Box 3, Folder 67)
    - Frisk, correspondence, undated (Box 3, Folder 68)
    - Wrong, manuscript, undated (Box 3, Folder 69)
    - Wrong, correspondence, undated (Box 3, Folder 70)
    - Wrong, cover art and reviews, undated (Box 3, Folder 71)
    - Try, first draft, undated (Box 3, Folder 72)
    - Try, early draft, undated (Box 3, Folder 73)
    - Try, early draft part 2, undated (Box 3, Folder 74)
    - Try, early draft part 3, undated (Box 3, Folder 74a)
    - Try, copyedited manuscript, undated (Box 3, Folder 75)
    - Try, manuscript--Walt Bode's editing, undated (Box 3, Folder 76)
    - Try, corrected page proofs, undated (Box 3, Folder 77)
    - Try, correspondence, undated (Box 3, Folder 78)
    - Try, Cooper and Yancy C. manuscript "Lari Pittman", undated (Box 3, Folder 80)
    - Try, Cooper and Yancy C. manuscript, undated (Box 3, Folder 81)
    - Try, Cooper and McKinney manuscript of interview of McKinney, undated (Box 3, Folder 82)
    - Try, Cooper and McKinney manuscript "The Great Hindu Cow Conspiracy", undated (Box 3, Folder 83)
    - Try, Cooper and McKinney manuscript "Pay for Your Pleasure", undated (Box 3, Folder 84)
    - Try, Casey McKinney background file, undated (Box 3, Folder 85)
    - Try, Casey McKinney background file--photos, undated (Box 3, Folder 86)
    - Try, Casey McKinney various manuscripts, undated (Box 3, Folder 87)
    - Try, Casey McKinney manuscript "Criminality and Other Themes", undated (Box 3, Folder 88)
    - Try, Casey McKinney manuscript "Atlanta, Dakota", undated (Box 3, Folder 89)
    - Try, Jeffrey Lee--manuscript "I Live Here", undated (Box 3, Folder 90)
    - Try, Ziggy Kramer background file, undated (Box 3, Folder 91)
    - Try, background images, undated (Box 3, Folder 92)
    - Try, reviews, undated (Box 3, Folder 93)
    - Try, reviews, undated (Box 3, Folder 94)
    - Try, press/reviews, undated (Box 3, Folder 95)
    - Try, press/cover art, undated (Box 3, Folder 96)
    - Jerk, draft, undated (Box 4, Folder 97)
    - Jerk, manuscript, undated (Box 4, Folder 98)
    - Jerk, manuscript, undated (Box 4, Folder 99)
    - Jerk, manuscript, undated (Box 4, Folder 100)
    - Jerk, galleys, undated (Box 4, Folder 101)
    - Jerk, correspondence, undated (Box 4, Folder 102)
    - Jerk, reviews/promotional material, undated (Box 4, Folder 103)
    - The Dream Police, manuscript, undated (Box 4, Folder 104)
    - The Dream Police, reviews/cover art, undated (Box 4, Folder 105)
    - Horror Hospital Unplugged, early draft, undated (Box 4, Folder 106)
    - Horror Hospital Unplugged, second expanded edition, undated (Box 4, Folder 107)
    - Horror Hospital Unplugged, uncorrected work copy, undated (Box 4, Folder 108)
    - Horror Hospital Unplugged, manuscript and slides, undated (Box 4, Folder 109)
    - Horror Hospital Unplugged, correspondence, undated (Box 4, Folder 110)
    - Horror Hospital Unplugged, River Phoenix File, undated (Box 4, Folder 111)
    - Horror Hospital Unplugged, manuscript by Keith Mayerson "A Child is Being Beaten", undated (Box 4, Folder 112)
    - Horror Hospital Unplugged, press, undated (Box 4, Folder 113)
    - Guide, early draft, undated (Box 4, Folder 114)
    - Guide, early draft, undated (Box 4, Folder 115)
    - Guide, early draft, undated (Box 4, Folder 116)
    - Guide, early draft, undated (Box 4, Folder 117)
    - Guide, later draft, undated (Box 4, Folder 118)
    - Guide, editor's copy, undated (Box 4, Folder 118a)
    - Guide, correspondence, undated (Box 4, Folder 119)
    - Guide, editorial correspondence, undated (Box 4, Folder 120)
    - Guide, manuscript Joel Westendorf and Dennis Cooper/Film proprosal, undated (Box 4, Folder 122)
    - Guide, manuscript Joel Westendorf and Dennis Cooper--Rave article early draft, undated (Box 4, Folder 123)
    - Guide, manuscript Joel Westendorf and Dennis Cooper--Rave article later draft, undated (Box 4, Folder 124)
    - Guide, background material--Joel Westendorf file, undated (Box 4, Folder 125)
    - Guide, background material--images, undated (Box 4, Folder 126)
    - Guide, background material--fax about interview with Leonardo di Caprio, undated (Box 4, Folder 127)
    - Guide, Blur, undated (Box 4, Folder 127a)
    - Guide, background material--interview with Leonardo di Caprio, undated (Box 4, Folder 128)
    - Guide, background material--Mitchell Watkins manuscript, undated (Box 4, Folder 129)
    - Guide, cover design, undated (Box 16, Folder 130a)
    - Guide, cover designs, undated (Box 4, Folder 130)
    - Guide, press, undated (Box 4, Folder 131)
    - Period, editorial proof, undated (Box 4, Folder 131a)
  - Subseries B: Book projects and related materials
    - Against Nature, manuscript, undated (Box 5, Folder 132)
    - Against Nature, Correspondence, undated (Box 5, Folder 133)
    - Against Nature, photos, undated (Box 5, Folder 134)
    - Against Nature, promotional material and reviews, undated (Box 5, Folder 135)
    - Boys from Outerspace, porno script by Cooper and Norman Yonemoto, undated (Box 5, Folder 136)
    - Boys I've Wanted, Christmas edition, undated (Box 5, Folder 137)
    - The Secret Lives of Teen Idols, Christmas edition, undated (Box 5, Folder 138)
    - Loss, Christmas edition, undated (Box 5, Folder 139)
    - Brian Winchester, Christmas edition, undated (Box 5, Folder 140)
    - Untitled Christmas edition, undated (Box 5, Folder 141)
    - Denny, Christmas edition, undated (Box 5, Folder 142)